<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-reddy-dprive-dns-profile-and-auth-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DPRIVE (D)TLS profile and DNS server auth">DPRIVE TLS/DTLS
    Profile and DNS server authentication</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>

          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Sara Dickinson" initials="S." surname="Dickinson">
      <organization>Sinodun Internet Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Magdalen Centre</street>

          <street>Oxford Science Park</street>

          <city>Oxford</city>

          <code>OX4 4GA</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sara@sinodun.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>California</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Prashanth Patil" initials="P." surname="Patil">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <street></street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>praspati@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>DPRIVE</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a Transport Layer Security (TLS) and Datagram
      TLS (DTLS) 1.2 profile for providing DNS privacy, and mechanisms the DNS
      client can use to authenticate the server providing DNS privacy.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>The DPRIVE working group has two active documents that provide DNS
      confidentiality, DNS over DTLS <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls"></xref> and DNS over TLS <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dns-over-tls"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document defines a profile of DTLS 1.2 <xref
      target="RFC6347"></xref> and TLS 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246"></xref> that
      offers DNS privacy. This profile defines the configuration options and
      protocol extensions to perform connection handshakes with the fewest
      round trips while maintaining privacy. It also discusses mechanisms the
      DNS client can use to authenticate the server providing DNS privacy.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="term" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="(D)TLS Profile">
      <t>This section defines the profile of DNS over DTLS and of DNS over
      TLS. Implementations compliant with this profile MUST implement all of
      the following items:<list style="symbols">
          <t><xref target="RFC7250">Raw public keys</xref>, which reduce the
          size of the ServerHello, and cannot obtain certificates (e.g., DNS
          resolvers on private networks). DNS client and DNS resolver need to
          support <xref target="RFC7250"></xref>, and raw public key-based
          authentication mechanism defined in <xref target="RFC7250"></xref>
          can be used by the client to authenticate the DNS resolver. DNS
          client needs to be configured with the SubjectPublicKeyInfo
          fingerprint of the DNS resolver, and;</t>

          <t>The interaction between the DNS client and the DNS server
          requires Transport Layer Security (TLS) and Datagram Transport Layer
          Security (DTLS) with a ciphersuite offering confidentiality
          protection and the guidance given in <xref target="RFC7525"></xref>
          must be followed to avoid attacks on (D)TLS.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>It is RECOMMENDED to implement the following items to improve
      performance:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t><xref target="RFC5077">TLS session resumption without server-side
          state</xref>, which eliminates the need for the server to retain
          cryptographic state for longer than necessary, and;</t>

          <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-falsestart">TLS False Start</xref>,
          which reduces round-trips by allowing the TLS second flight of
          messages (ChangeCipherSpec) to also contain the (encrypted) DNS
          query, and;</t>

          <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-cached-info">Cached Information
          Extension</xref>, which avoids transmitting the server's certificate
          and certificate chain if the client has cached that information from
          a previous TLS handshake.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Authenticating the DNS Privacy Server">
      <t>DNS privacy requires encrypting the query (and response) from passive
      attacks. Such encryption typically provides integrity protection as a
      side-effect, which means on-path attackers cannot simply inject bogus
      DNS responses. However, to provide stronger protection from active
      attackers pretending to be the server, the server itself needs to be
      authenticated.</t>

      <t>To authenticate the server providing DNS privacy, the DNS client
      needs to be configured with the names or IP addresses of those DNS
      privacy servers. The server certificate MUST contain DNS-ID
      (subjectAltName) as described in Section 4.1 of <xref
      target="RFC6125"></xref>. DNS names and IP addresses can be contained in
      the subjectAltName entries. The client MUST use the rules and guidelines
      given in section 6 of <xref target="RFC6125"></xref> to validate the DNS
      server identity.</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble>This could be implemented by adding the certificate name to
        the /etc/resolv.conf file, such as below:</preamble>

        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  nameserver 8.8.8.8
  certificate google-public-dns.google.com
  nameserver 208.67.220.220
  certificate resolver.opendns.com
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>For DNS privacy servers that don't have a certificate trust chain
      (e.g., because they are on a home network or a corporate network), the
      configured list of DNS privacy servers can contain the Subject Public
      Key Info (SPKI) fingerprint of the DNS privacy server (i.e., a simple
      whitelist of name and SPKI fingerprint). The public key is used for the
      same reasons HTTP pinning <xref target="RFC7469"></xref> uses the public
      key. Raw public key-based authentication mechanism defined in <xref
      target="RFC7250"></xref> can be also used to authenticate the DNS
      server.</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble>This could be implemented by adding the SPKI fingerprint to
        the /etc/resolv.conf file, such as below (line split for Internet
        Draft formatting):</preamble>

        <artwork><![CDATA[
  nameserver 192.168.1.1
  sha256 : "d6qzRu9zOECb90Uez27xWltNsj0e1Md7GkYYkVoZWmM="]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The only algorithm considered at this time is "sha256", i.e., the
      hash algorithm SHA256 <xref target="RFC6234"></xref>; additional
      algorithms may be allowed for use in this context in the future. The
      quoted-string is a sequence of base 64 digits: the base64-encoded SPKI
      Fingerprint <xref target="RFC4648"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Common problems with DNS Privacy">
      <t>This section describes problems common to any DNS privacy solution.
      To achieve DNS privacy an encrypted and integrity-protected channel is
      needed between the client and server. This channel can be blocked, and
      the client needs to react to such blockages. The encrypted traffic is
      not normal DNS traffic, but rather is a cryptographic handshake followed
      by encrypted payloads. There can be firewalls, other security devices,
      or intercepting DNS proxies which block the non-DNS traffic or otherwise
      react negatively (e.g., quarantining the host for suspicious
      behavior).</t>

      <t>Using DNS privacy with an authenticated server is most preferred, DNS
      privacy with an unauthenticated server is next preferred, and plain DNS
      is least preferred. This section gives a non-normative discussion on
      common behaviors and choices.</t>

      <t>An implementation MAY attempt to obtain DNS privacy by contacting DNS
      servers on the local network (provided by DHCP) and on the Internet, and
      make those attempts in parallel to reduce user impact. If DNS privacy
      cannot be successfully negotiated for whatever reason, the client can do
      three things: <list style="numbers">
          <t>refuse to send DNS queries on this network, which means the
          client cannot make effective use of this network, as modern networks
          require DNS; or,</t>

          <t>use opportunistic security, as described in <xref
          target="RFC7435"></xref>. or,</t>

          <t>send plain DNS queries on this network, which means no DNS
          privacy is provided.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Heuristics can improve this situation, but only to a degree (e.g.,
      previous success of DNS privacy on this network may be reason to alert
      the user about failure to establish DNS privacy on this network now).
      Still, the client (in cooperation with the end user) has to decide to
      use the network without the protection of DNS privacy.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>With opportunistic privacy, a client might learn of a (D)TLS-enabled
      recursive DNS resolver from an untrusted source (such as DHCP while
      roaming), it might or might not validate the TLS certificate. These
      choices maximize availability and performance, but they leave the client
      vulnerable to on-path attacks that remove privacy. Opportunistic privacy
      can be used by any current client, but it only provides guaranteed
      privacy when there are no on-path active attackers.</t>

      <t>Security considerations discussed in DTLS <xref
      target="RFC7435"></xref> and TLS <xref target="RFC7435"></xref> apply to
      this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TODO</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7525"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6125"
?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4648"
?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7435"
?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6234"
?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7469"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6347"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7250"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-dprive-dns-over-tls' ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tls-falsestart"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tls-cached-info"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5077"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
